What did you say?
뭐라고 하셨나요?
His...
그의...
His Majesty passed away.
폐하께서 돌아가셨습니다.
His Majesty passed away?
폐하께서 돌아가셨는가?
Your Highness,
전하,
please go with me now.
지금 나와 함께 가주세요.
The palace is in chaos.
궁전은 혼란에 빠졌습니다.
If we don't leave now, it'll be too late!
지금 떠나지 않으면 너무 늦을 거예요!
Sachets and trinkets! Come and take a look!
향 주머니와 장신구! 와서 살펴보세요!
A few days ago, His Majesty
며칠 전 폐하
gave me this token,
나에게 이 토큰을 줬어
saying that now Biantang is not at peace,
지금 Biantang은 평화롭지 않다고 말하면서
and that if anything were to happen in the palace,
그리고 만약 무슨 일이 일어나면 궁전에서
I was to take you away.
나는 당신을 데려가기로 했어요.
I didn't understand
이해하지 못했어요
what he meant at the time,
그 당시 그가 무슨 뜻이었는지,
but I didn't dare to ask.
하지만 감히 물어볼 수가 없었습니다.
I never expected...
전혀 예상하지 못했습니다...
Listen to me!
내 말을 들어보세요!
You're not allowed to go anywhere!
아무데도 갈 수 없습니다!
Just stay in the mansion.
그냥 저택에 있어라.
You, a deposed princess,
너는 폐위된 공주야
and I, a useless prince,
그리고 나는 쓸모없는 왕자야
are a match made in heaven.
천국에서 이루어진 일치입니다.
I will achieve every single thing
나는 모든 것을 성취할 것이다
I promised you!
약속했어요!
If you don't want to get married yet,
아직 결혼하고 싶지 않다면
we can pretend today's wedding never happened.
우리는 그런 척 할 수 있어 오늘 결혼식은 열리지 않았어.
I can keep waiting for you,
계속 기다릴 수 있어요
until you fall in love with me,
네가 나와 ​​사랑에 빠질 때까지
until the day you truly want to be my wife.
그날까지 당신은 정말로 내 아내가 되고 싶어하는군요.
Chun'er!
춘어!
No matter what you've been through,
어떤 일을 겪었든
I will not leave you.
나는 당신을 떠나지 않을 것입니다.
For all those who wronged you,
당신에게 잘못을 저지른 모든 사람들을 위해
I will make them pay double for you.
나는 그들이 당신을 위해 두 배의 돈을 지불하게 할 것입니다.
Then can you temporarily treat me as that person,
그러면 일시적으로 할 수 있나요? 나를 그런 사람으로 대해줘
until you truly forget him
그를 정말로 잊을 때까지
and are no longer in pain?
더 이상 고통스럽지 않나요?
As long as you are willing,
당신이 원하는 한,
I can always accompany you.
나는 언제나 당신과 동행할 수 있습니다.
Li Yan...
리얀...
You liar.
당신은 거짓말쟁이입니다.
What gives you the right to make decisions for me?
무엇이 당신에게 권리를 주는가 나를 위해 결정을 내리라고?
You said
네가 말했지
you would make anything
넌 무엇이든 만들 수 있을 거야
you promised me happen.
당신은 나에게 일어날 것이라고 약속했습니다.
But what about now?
하지만 지금은 어떻습니까?
Where are you now?
지금 어디 있나요?
[REBIRTH]
[환생]
[Episode 23]
[23화]
How is it?
어때요?
Any news of His Majesty and the main force?
폐하의 어떤 소식이라도 그리고 주력은?
Your Highness.
전하.
The post road back to Great Yan is just ahead at the foot of the mountain.
Great Yan으로 돌아가는 우편 도로 산기슭 바로 앞에 있어요.
But I asked the nearby villagers,
그런데 근처 마을 사람들에게 물어보니
and none of them saw any troops passing through.
그리고 그들 중 누구도 지나가는 군대를 보았습니다.
However, on my way back,
하지만 돌아오는 길에
I found this.
나는 이것을 발견했다.
It was likely left behind by soldiers who, like us,
군인들이 두고 간 것 같은데, 우리처럼
got separated from the main force.
주력부대에서 분리됐다.
Your Highness.
전하.
Our Great Yan has suffered a crushing defeat,
우리 대연이 고생했어요 참패했어
and the main force has been scattered.
그리고 주력은 흩어졌습니다.
If you ask me, searching further is pointless.
당신이 나에게 묻는다면, 더 이상 검색하는 것은 의미가 없습니다.
What did you say?
뭐라고 하셨나요?
Something must have happened to His Majesty and General Cheng.
무슨 일이 있었나 봐요 폐하와 청 장군에게.
Otherwise, they would have come back for us.
그렇지 않으면, 그들은 우리를 위해 돌아왔을 것입니다.
Your Highness,
전하,
we brothers don't want to go back.
우리 형제들은 돌아가고 싶지 않아요.
Over the years, Great Yan has been at war with Great Yong,
수년에 걸쳐, Great Yan은 Great Yong과 전쟁을 벌였습니다.
and all the men in my family were conscripted
그리고 내 가족의 남자들은 모두 징집됐다
and have long since died in battle.
전투에서 죽은 지 오래되었습니다.
Even if I go back to the Capital of Great Yan,
다시 돌아간다 해도 대연의 수도로
there is no home left for me there.
거기에는 나에게 남은 집이 없습니다.
You might as well just let us go.
그냥 우리를 보내주는 게 나을 수도 있어요.
Your Highness,
전하,
I'm just like him.
나도 그와 똑같습니다.
I'm the only one left in my family.
우리 가족 중에 나 혼자만 남았다.
Great Yan is already poor,
Great Yan은 이미 가난해요
and now the taxes are heavy.
이제 세금이 무겁습니다.
We want to leave Great Yan
Great Yan을 떠나고 싶어요
and find a more prosperous place.
그리고 좀 더 번영하는 곳을 찾아보세요.
We heard Biantang is a good place.
비안탕이 좋은 곳이라고 들었어요.
Yes, let us go.
응, 가자.
You are all soldiers of Great Yan!
너희들은 모두 대연의 병사들이다!
According to Great Yan's military law,
대연의 군사법에 따르면,
leaving now would make you deserters!
지금 떠나면 탈영병이 될 것입니다!
You know better than I do
당신은 나보다 더 잘 알고 있어요
what deserters will face!
탈영병들은 어떤 일을 겪게 될까요!
The Black Eagle Army is His Majesty's most trusted guard
검은 독수리 군대 폐하께서 가장 신뢰하시는 경비원은
and the pride of Great Yan.
그리고 Great Yan의 자부심.
Now that Great Yan is in distress,
이제 Great Yan이 곤경에 빠졌으니,
you're going to abandon your honor?
명예를 버리겠다고?
The Black Eagle Army has shed blood on battlefields for years,
흑수리군이 피를 흘렸다 수년간 전장에서
suffering countless casualties.
수많은 사상자를 냈다.
What was it all for?
그게 다 무슨 목적이었나요?
If you return
돌아오면
to the Capital of Great Yan with me now,
지금 나와 함께 대연의 수도로
you will be escorting the Princess Consort
당신은 공주 배우자를 호위하게 될 것입니다
of Great Yan back for His Majesty.
대연이 폐하께 돌아왔습니다.
I promise you in the name of His Majesty
폐하의 이름으로 약속드립니다
and the Helian Tribe,
그리고 헬리안 부족,
you will not only get gold, silver, and horses,
금, 은뿐만 아니라 그리고 말,
but also the title of Centurion
그리고 백부장이라는 칭호도
or even Chiliarch.
아니면 칠리아크라도.
I am willing to escort you back to the Capital of Great Yan,
나는 당신을 호위할 의향이 있습니다 대연의 수도로 돌아가
even if it costs my life!
내 목숨을 앗아가더라도!
I am willing to escort you,
기꺼이 당신을 호위하겠습니다.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
You promised us promotion and wealth,
우리에게 승진과 부를 약속하셨죠,
and it's true.
그리고 그것은 사실이다.
But we were the ones who brought up leaving in the first place.
하지만 키운 건 우리였지 우선 떠나는 것.
We're afraid you'll go back on your word
당신이 약속을 어길까 두렵습니다
and settle accounts with us later.
나중에 우리와 결산해 보세요.
So there are some things
그래서 몇 가지가 있습니다
we want to make clear to you now.
우리는 지금 당신에게 분명히 하고 싶습니다.
I am the Princess Consort of Great Yan.
나는 대연공주빈이다.
How could I break my word to you?
내가 어떻게 당신에게 한 약속을 어길 수 있겠습니까?
Put down your weapons now,
이제 무기를 내려놔,
and I will act as if nothing ever happened.
그리고 나는 행동할 것이다 마치 아무 일도 일어나지 않은 것처럼.
How about we put it this way?
이렇게 말하면 어떨까요?
In this desolate wilderness,
이 황량한 황야에서
if anything were to happen to Consort Helian,
무슨 일이라도 일어나면 헬리안 배우자에게
then no one would know we are deserters.
그러면 아무도 우리가 탈영병이라는 것을 알지 못할 것입니다.
Instead,
대신
people might even think
사람들은 이렇게 생각할지도 몰라
we died heroically at Longyin Pass.
우리는 용인관에서 영웅적으로 죽었습니다.
Don't come over! Don't come over!
오지 마세요! 오지 마세요!
General Huan?
후안 장군?
You...
당신은...
Aren't you...
그렇지 않나요...
Aren't I already dead?
나는 이미 죽은 것이 아닌가?
Take this to protect yourself.
자신을 보호하려면 이것을 가져가세요.
Be careful not to get stabbed in the back by your own people.
칼에 찔리지 않도록 조심하세요 뒤에서는 당신네 사람들이요.
Wait.
기다리다.
Why are you here?
당신은 왜 여기에 있습니까?
Does His Majesty know?
폐하께서는 알고 계십니까?
I saved your life
내가 당신의 생명을 구했어요
only because you are a woman.
단지 당신이 여자이기 때문에요.
If you keep asking so many questions,
계속 질문을 많이 하면
I'll throw you back up that mountain.
널 그 산 위로 던져줄게
There are far more beasts up there than here.
짐승이 훨씬 더 많아 여기보다 거기 위에요.
You...
당신은...
Stop pretending.
척하지 마세요.
I'm not falling for your tricks on men.
나는 당신의 남자에 대한 속임수에 빠지지 않습니다.
It's been so many days.
정말 많은 날이 지났습니다.
Why is she still so weak?
그녀는 왜 아직도 그렇게 약한 걸까요?
When the body is overworked, the spleen is affected.
몸이 과로할 때, 비장이 영향을 받습니다.
Excessive thinking affects the heart.
과도한 생각은 마음에 영향을 미칩니다.
Vital energy gets trapped and cannot circulate,
생명 에너지가 갇혀 순환할 수 없습니다.
causing blood and qi to gradually deplete.
혈액과 기가 점차 고갈됩니다.
Stop rambling.
방황하지 마세요.
Put it simply.
간단히 말해.
Simply put,
간단히 말해서,
she has internal heat,
그녀는 내부에 열이 있어요
and combined with fatigue
그리고 피로와 결합
and mental strain, she is now feeling unwell.
그리고 정신적 긴장, 그녀는 지금 몸이 좋지 않습니다.
She is fine now.
그녀는 이제 괜찮습니다.
Just needs proper rest and recovery.
적절한 휴식과 회복이 필요합니다.
Including today's medicine,
오늘의 약을 포함하여
there are 5 doses in total,
총 5회 분량이 있습니다.
and 2 visit fees.
그리고 2 방문 수수료.
That's 10 coins.
10코인입니다.
Are you robbing us?
우리를 강탈하고 있습니까?
My prices are clearly marked and fair.
내 가격은 명확하게 표시되어 있고 공정합니다.
What are you doing?
뭐하세요?
Are you kidding me?
농담하는 거야?
What are you doing with this?
이걸로 뭐하는 거야?
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원하세요?
Here.
여기.
It's freshly made and full measure.
갓 만들어졌고 완전한 측정이 이루어졌습니다.
It usually sells for 10 coins in my shop.
내 가게에서는 보통 10코인에 팔아요.
You... Come on.
당신은... 어서.
Why give a doctor
의사에게 왜
a hammer?
망치?
Besides,
게다가,
you're just a helper here.
당신은 여기서 도우미 일뿐입니다.
Your manager is away for a few days,
당신의 관리자가 며칠 동안 자리를 비웠습니다.
and you think you can just take it upon yourself
그리고 넌 그냥 할 수 있다고 생각하지? 스스로 책임져라
to use goods from the shop as collateral?
상점의 물건을 담보로 사용하려면?
This scrap metal
이 고철
is worth 2 coins at most.
최대 2코인의 가치가 있습니다.
What are you doing with that blade?
그 칼날로 뭐하는 거야?
Don't mess with me.
나한테 장난치지 마.
It's not worth risking your life.
목숨을 걸고 할 가치가 없습니다.
Here.
여기.
This blade can sell for at least 10 coins.
이 칼날은 최소 10코인에 판매될 수 있습니다.
Keep the change.
변경 사항을 유지하십시오.
I'm not a butcher.
나는 정육점이 아닙니다.
Why give me a blade?
왜 나에게 칼날을 주나요?
No.
아니요.
You can't be a penny short.
당신은 한 푼도 부족할 수 없습니다.
Are you taking advantage of us?
당신은 우리를 이용하고 있습니까?
Easy! Easy!
쉬운! 쉬운!
You may break it!
깨뜨릴 수도 있어요!
General Huan.
환 장군.
This hairpiece is pure gold.
이 헤어피스는 순금입니다.
It's worth a hundred times the consultation fee.
백배의 가치가 있어요 상담비.
Hearing you speak just now,
방금 당신이 말하는 것을 들었는데,
you're an old physician in this town.
당신은 이 마을의 늙은 의사예요.
Huan Huan and I are old friends.
Huan Huan과 나는 오랜 친구입니다.
I've been recuperating here these days.
요즘 여기서 요양하고 있어요.
If there's anything wrong with this gold,
이 금에 문제가 있으면
just come back to me.
그냥 나에게 돌아와.
Fine, I'll trust you this time.
좋아, 이번에는 당신을 믿을게요.
Goodbye.
안녕히 가세요.
You tigress. She-devil.
이 호랑이. 그녀는 악마입니다.
Witch.
마녀.
She-
그녀-
Thank you, General Huan.
감사합니다, 환 장군님.
You're back?
돌아왔나요?
This is the stone-pot chicken of Great Yan that I specially made.
이게 돌솥닭이에요 내가 특별히 만든 Great Yan의 것입니다.
You've been away from the Capital for so long.
당신은 수도에서 멀리 떨어져 있었습니다 너무 오랫동안.
You must not have had it in a long time.
당신은 오랫동안 그것을 가지고 있지 않았을 것입니다.
And this.
그리고 이것.
These are horse milk cakes unique to the Helian Tribe.
이건 말고기 케이크예요 헬리안 부족 특유의
I went to several pastry shops in town
시내에 있는 여러 페이스트리 가게에 갔어
before I finally found them.
마침내 그들을 발견하기 전에.
Try some and see
몇 가지를 시험해보고 확인해 보세요
if it tastes the same as the ones in the Capital of Great Yan.
맛이 똑같다면 Great Yan의 수도에 있는 것과 같습니다.
General Huan,
환 장군,
stop pretending to be cold.
추운 척 그만해.
It's tiring.
피곤해요.
I saw your place was rather simple,
네 집은 꽤 단순한 것 같던데,
so I brought you some things.
그래서 몇 가지를 가져왔습니다.
I walked a long way
먼 길을 걸었어
to buy this quilt for the bed.
이 침대용 이불을 사려고요.
And this heater.
그리고 이 히터.
The weather here seems even colder
여기 날씨가 더 추운 것 같아요
than in the Capital of Great Yan.
Great Yan의 수도보다.
And these wildflowers.
그리고 이 야생화들.
A woman should look like a woman.
여자는 여자답게 보여야 합니다.
Let's eat.
먹자.
Hand me your bowl.
그릇을 나에게 건네주세요.
You sold all your jewelry?
보석을 다 팔았나요?
Those are just worldly possessions.
그것은 단지 세상적인 소유물일 뿐입니다.
There are plenty in the palace of Great Yan.
많이 있다 Great Yan의 궁전에서.
I still have some money left.
아직 돈이 좀 남아 있어요.
Keep it for your future use.
나중에 사용할 수 있도록 보관하세요.
Tell me.
말해 주세요.
What do you want?
당신은 무엇을 원하세요?
I want to borrow your horse.
나는 당신의 말을 빌리고 싶습니다.
I heard in the town
마을에서 들었어
that Yan Xun has returned safely to the Capital of Great Yan.
Yan Xun이 무사히 돌아왔다고 Great Yan의 수도로.
I should go back too.
나도 돌아가야 해.
I know His Majesty has failed you
폐하께서 당신을 실망시키셨다는 걸 압니다
and the Snowy Region Tribe.
그리고 눈 덮인 지역 부족.
But...
하지만...
Great Yan is now at a critical moment of survival.
그레이트 얀 지금은 생존의 중요한 순간에 있습니다.
I must go back to help His Majesty.
저는 폐하를 돕기 위해 돌아가야 합니다.
The Snowy Region Tribe has been loyal to Great Yan for generations.
설국 부족은 충성을 다해 왔습니다 여러 세대에 걸쳐 Great Yan에게.
General Huan, you...
Huan 장군님, 당신은...
Say no more.
더 이상 말하지 마세요.
General Huan!
환 장군!
That horse was originally
그 말은 원래
a wild horse from the Huolei Plains of Great Yan.
화레이 평원의 야생마 그레이트얀의.
It probably wants to go back too.
아마 그도 돌아가고 싶어할 것이다.
Take it with you.
당신과 함께 가져 가라.
[General Xiuli's Mansion]
[수리 장군의 저택]
His Majesty told me before he passed away
폐하께서 돌아가시기 전에 나에게 말씀하셨죠
that he had an agreement with you.
그 사람이 당신과 계약을 맺었다고 하더군요.
Once you and General Chu
일단 당신과 추 장군
returned victorious from battle,
전투에서 승리하여 돌아왔습니다
he would lend you 500 imperial guards.
그는 당신에게 황실 경비병 500명을 빌려주겠다고 했습니다.
Now,
이제,
these 500 guards are all under my command.
이 500명의 경비병은 모두 내 지휘하에 있다.
I am to
나는
hand this token over to you
이 토큰을 당신에게 넘겨주세요
on His Majesty's behalf.
폐하를 대신하여.
It can be considered the fulfillment of His Majesty's promise.
이행이라고 볼 수 있다 폐하의 약속.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
When I return from Ximeng,
Ximeng에서 돌아오면
I will return them to you.
나는 그것을 당신에게 돌려줄 것입니다.
Young master,
젊은 스승님,
everything we need to bring is here.
우리가 가져와야 할 모든 것이 여기에 있습니다.
I've packed winter quilts
겨울 이불을 챙겼어요
and coats made of sheepskin and deerskin,
양가죽과 사슴가죽으로 만든 코트,
enough to keep us warm in Ximeng.
Ximeng에서 우리를 따뜻하게 유지하기에 충분합니다.
There's also a chest of gold and silver utensils,
가슴도 있네 금은 도구,
which can be sold for money if needed later.
돈으로 팔 수 있는 것 나중에 필요하다면.
Along with a box of Xiao Ran's medicine
샤오란의 약 한 상자와 함께
and Lady Chu's and Minglu's luggage,
그리고 Lady Chu와 Minglu의 짐,
these two carriages should be enough.
이 두 개의 마차이면 충분할 것입니다.
Okay.
좋아요.
We're going to Ximeng
우리는 시멍으로 갈 거야
to get the antidote for your young master,
네 젊은 주인을 위한 해독제를 구하려면
not to settle down.
정착하지 말라고.
If you ask me,
나에게 묻는다면,
we should bring all the hidden weapons
숨겨진 무기를 모두 가져와야 해
from Qingshan Manor.
칭산 매너 출신.
Needles, poisons—
바늘, 독—
everything.
모든 것.
Yes, you're right.
네, 당신 말이 맞아요.
Why didn't I think of that?
나는 왜 그 생각을 하지 못했는가?
Shiyi.
시이.
There's no need.
필요하지 않습니다.
Master,
선생님,
have you seen Lady Chu?
레이디 추 봤어?
I went to her room this morning,
오늘 아침에 그녀의 방에 갔어
and she wasn't there.
그리고 그녀는 거기에 없었습니다.
When I was feeding the horses this morning,
말들에게 먹이를 주고 있을 때 오늘 아침
I saw Lady Chu leaving in a carriage.
나는 추 부인이 마차를 타고 떠나는 것을 보았습니다.
She said she was going to the palace.
그녀는 궁전에 간다고 말했습니다.
What's this?
이건 뭐죠?
This was left by His Majesty before he passed away.
이것은 폐하께서 남기신 것입니다 그가 세상을 떠나기 전에.
At that time,
당시
the news of Biantang defeating Great Yan's Black Eagle Army
비안탕의 소식 대연의 흑수리군을 격파
had just arrived.
방금 도착했습니다.
His Majesty said
폐하께서 말씀하셨다
he wanted to grant you a title
그는 당신에게 칭호를 부여하고 싶어했어요
more impressive than mine and Li Qi's.
나와 Li Qi의 것보다 더 인상적이었습니다.
But he never decided on one.
그러나 그는 결코 결정하지 않았습니다.
Why is this here?
이게 왜 여기 있지?
His Majesty had been on the throne for months
폐하 몇 달 동안 왕좌에 있었어
but never established a harem.
그러나 하렘을 설립한 적은 없습니다.
The Court of Rites has advised him many times,
의식의 법원 그에게 여러 번 조언을 해줬어요
but he never approved.
하지만 그는 결코 승인하지 않았습니다.
Actually, His Majesty wanted to wait for you to come back
사실, 폐하 네가 돌아올 때까지 기다리고 싶었어
and express his feelings to you in person.
그리고 그의 감정을 당신에게 직접 표현하십시오.
He said that if you agreed,
그는 당신이 동의하면
this decree
이 법령
would name you Empress of Biantang.
당신을 비안탕 황후라 부를 것입니다.
But...
하지만...
he said you probably wouldn't agree.
그는 아마 당신이 동의하지 않을 것이라고 말했습니다.
So most likely,
아마도
he would just make you a great general,
그는 당신을 위대한 장군으로 만들어 줄 거예요
and send you off in glory
그리고 당신을 영광스럽게 보내세요
to marry the man you love.
당신이 사랑하는 남자와 결혼하기 위해.
A country cannot be without a ruler for a single day.
통치자가 없으면 나라가 존재할 수 없다 하루 동안.
Biantang has just emerged from war,
Biantang은 전쟁에서 막 등장했습니다.
and the court is still unstable.
법원은 여전히 ​​불안정하다.
This is a turbulent time.
지금은 혼란스러운 시기입니다.
Since Emperor Ruili had no other heirs
루일리 황제에게는 다른 상속자가 없었기 때문에
besides the late emperor,
고(故) 황제 외에,
we should select a virtuous and capable prince
우리는 선한 것을 선택해야 한다 그리고 유능한 왕자
of the same generation from the imperial clan
같은 세대의 제국 일족 출신
to succeed the throne immediately
즉시 왕위를 계승하려면
and restore peace to the realm.
그리고 왕국에 평화를 회복시키십시오.
That being said,
즉,
this concerns the throne after all.
이것은 결국 왕좌에 관한 것입니다.
Which prince within the royal clan would be suitable?
왕실 일족 중 어느 왕자 적합할까요?
Well...
음...
What about Prince of Jing?
징왕자는 어떻습니까?
He is Emperor Ruili's blood brother,
그는 루이리 황제의 혈형입니다.
so his accession to the throne would be legitimate.
그래서 그의 왕위 계승은 합법적 일 것입니다.
That would not be appropriate.
그것은 적절하지 않습니다.
Although Prince of Jing is in his prime,
징왕은 전성기이지만,
he was born with a weak constitution
그는 허약한 체질로 태어났다
and has always relied on medicine.
항상 약에 의존해 왔습니다.
He cannot even do basic riding and archery.
그 사람은 할 수조차 없어 기본 승마와 양궁.
How could he bear the responsibility of ruling a nation?
그 사람이 어떻게 책임을 질 수 있겠어요? 나라를 다스리는 것?
In my view,
내 생각에는
it would be better to recommend Prince of An.
더 좋을 것입니다 안왕자를 추천합니다.
Prince of An comes from a military background
안왕자 군인 출신이야
and has military achievements.
그리고 군사적 업적을 가지고 있습니다.
His accession would win public support.
그의 가입은 대중의지지를 얻을 것입니다.
That would not be appropriate!
그것은 적절하지 않을 것입니다!
Prince of An has close ties with the Zhou family of the southern region,
안왕자는 다음과 긴밀한 관계를 맺고 있다. 남부 지역의 주 가문,
and his wife is from that family.
그의 아내도 그 가문 출신이에요.
Lord He, have you forgotten the lesson
주님, 교훈을 잊으셨나요
from the chaos of the previous dynasty caused by powerful in-laws?
이전 왕조의 혼란 속에서 강력한 시댁 때문에?
Chancellor,
장관님,
General Xiuli,
슈리 장군,
and Left General of Cavalry have arrived!
그리고 좌 기병대 장군이 도착했습니다!
It's the late emperor's son, Prince Xiuyi.
고(故) 황제의 아들 슈이왕(秦王)입니다.
Prince Xiuyi is the late emperor's son.
슈이왕자는 고(故) 황제의 아들이다.
Since the late emperor has passed away,
고(故) 황제가 세상을 떠났으므로
it is only natural that his only child should ascend the throne.
그의 외동아들인 것은 당연하다. 왕위에 올라야 한다.
Although Prince Xiuyi is the late emperor's son,
비록 슈이 왕자 고(故) 황제의 아들은
his mother, Zhan Ziming,
그의 어머니, Zhan Ziming,
is the sister of the convicted official Zhan Ziyu.
여동생이에요 유죄 판결을 받은 공무원 Zhan Ziyu의 말입니다.
The late emperor was kind
고인이 된 황제는 친절했어요
and spared her only because she was pregnant.
그리고 그녀를 살려주었다 단지 그녀가 임신했다는 이유만으로.
How can he now be considered a candidate for the throne?
이제 그는 어떻게 간주될 수 있는가? 왕위 후보?
Moreover, Prince Xiuyi is not even one year old.
게다가 슈이왕자는 한 살도 안 됐어요.
He is still an infant,
그는 아직 유아입니다.
unable to speak or walk.
말하거나 걸을 수 없습니다.
How could he possibly sit firmly on the throne?
그가 어떻게 그럴 수 있었을까? 왕좌에 굳건히 앉았느냐?
A weak ruler ruling a strong state
약한 통치자가 강한 국가를 다스리다
is a sign of impending chaos in the nation.
혼란이 닥칠 징조다 전국에서.
Indeed.
물론.
Grand Secretary Liu, General Sun.
Liu 총서기, Sun 장군.
This concerns the throne.
이것은 왕좌에 관한 것입니다.
You two must...
너희 둘은 꼭...
Here's the late emperor's posthumous edict!
여기가 고(故) 황제의 묘소다. 사후 칙령!
This edict...
이 칙령은...
General Xiuli, Chu Qiao,
Xiuli 장군, Chu Qiao,
is hereby granted the title of Consort Xiuli.
이에 따라 부여됩니다 배우자 Xiuli의 칭호.
If she gives birth to a prince in the future,
그녀가 출산한다면 미래의 왕자에게
she will be named Empress of Biantang.
그녀는 변당황후로 임명될 것이다.
Now that the late emperor has passed away
이제 고(故) 황제가 세상을 떠났으니
and the prince is still young,
왕자는 아직 어려요
for the sake of Biantang's future, the Consort
비안탕의 미래를 위해 배우자
has decided to adopt Prince Xiuyi.
슈이 왕자를 입양하기로 결정했습니다.
With his mother's noble status,
그의 어머니의 고귀한 지위와 함께,
why can't Prince Xiuyi take the throne?
왜 슈이 왕자는 왕위를 차지하지 못합니까?
The edict is here.
칙령이 여기에 있습니다.
If anyone has doubts,
의심스러운 사람이 있으면
you may come and take a look.
오셔서 구경하셔도 됩니다.
Is this really the late emperor's edict?
이것이 과연 선제의 칙령인가?
General Chu,
추 장군,
are you sure you want to do this?
정말 이 일을 하시겠습니까?
I just need to complete the imperial edict, right?
완료해야만 해요 황실칙령 맞죠?
There are no errors in the signature and date.
오류가 없습니다. 서명과 날짜에.
With you, Lord Sun and Lord Liu, as witnesses,
당신과 함께, Lord Sun과 Lord Liu, 증인으로서
I believe the ministers will not dare to question it.
나는 장관들을 믿는다. 감히 의문을 제기하지 못할 것입니다.
Since I have adopted Xiuyi as my son,
나는 Xiuyi를 아들로 입양했기 때문에
I am considered to have a son.
아들이 있는 것으로 간주됩니다.
According to the late emperor's edict,
고(故) 황제의 칙령에 따르면,
I can be conferred the title of Empress Dowager.
수여받을 수 있어요 황후의 칭호.
My son is still young,
내 아들은 아직 어려요
so the Empress Dowager can act as regent.
그래서 황후는 섭정 역할을 할 수 있습니다.
You are all pillars of the state.
여러분은 모두 국가의 기둥입니다.
Can you devise plans for Biantang
비안탕에 대한 계획을 세울 수 있나요
and its people,
그리고 그 사람들,
and help the late emperor's infant son
고 황제의 어린 아들을 도와주세요
secure this empire?
이 제국을 확보하시겠습니까?
Empress Dowager, you are making plans for the sake of
황태후, 당신은
the late emperor and the people.
를 위해 계획을 세우고 있어요 고(故) 황제와 국민.
We second the motion.
우리는 두 번째 동의를 구했습니다.
Let me tell you the truth.
진실을 말하겠습니다.
You've been set up by us.
당신은 우리에 의해 설정되었습니다.
We were sure that after seeing the edict,
우리는 칙령을 본 후
you would definitely stay for the little prince.
당신은 분명히 머물 것입니다 어린왕자를 위해서.
If you regret it now...
지금 후회한다면...
The edict has been issued.
칙령이 내려졌습니다.
How can this be treated as a game?
이걸 어떻게 게임으로 취급할 수 있나요?
As for the enthronement ceremony,
즉위식은
we will need your help, Grand Secretary Liu.
우리는 당신의 도움이 필요합니다 류 수석.
Three days from now is an auspicious day.
지금부터 3일은 상서로운 날이다.
I will urge the Ministry of Rites and the Ministry of Works
예식부에 촉구하겠습니다 그리고 노동부
to prepare everything as quickly as possible.
모든 것을 준비하기 위해 가능한 한 빨리.
Thank you.
감사합니다.
This was all your bad idea.
이것은 모두 당신의 나쁜 생각이었습니다.
Miss Chu really is unfortunate.
미스츄 정말 안타깝네요.
Biantang is now hanging by a thread.
현재 비앙탕은 실에 매달려 있습니다.
If chaos rises again, everyone will suffer when the country falls.
다시 혼돈이 닥치면 모두들 나라가 망하면 고통받을 것이다.
Do you think only the common people will suffer?
일반인들만 생각하시나요? 고통받을 것인가?
You, me,
너, 나,
and Miss Chu—
그리고 미스 추—
aren't we all part of it?
우리 모두가 그것의 일부가 아닌가?
[The border between Great Yan and Great Yong]
[국경 Great Yan과 Great Yong 사이]
Your Highness!
전하!
Why can't you keep your composure?
왜 평정심을 유지할 수 없나요?
Your Highness.
전하.
Only you can still keep your composure now.
너만 지금도 평정심을 유지할 수 있습니다.
Our mission of supporting Biantang this time
Biantang을 지원하는 우리의 사명 이번에는
has indeed been exhausting.
정말 지쳤어요.
In a few days,
며칠 안에,
we will be able to return to camp to rest.
우리는 캠프로 돌아가 휴식을 취할 수 있을 것입니다.
Your Highness,
전하,
we are not afraid of hardship.
우리는 고난을 두려워하지 않습니다.
It was us who submitted the military report
제출한 사람은 우리였어 군사 보고서
to His Majesty this time.
이번에는 폐하께.
It hasn't yet reached Zhenhuangcheng,
아직 Zhenhuangcheng에 도달하지 않았습니다.
and the Thirteenth Prince has already submitted a memorial against us.
그리고 열세 번째 왕자는 이미 우리를 상대로 기념비를 제출했습니다.
The charge is extremely serious,
혐의가 매우 심각합니다.
accusing us of unauthorized troop deployment and harboring treasonous ambitions.
우리를 무단 병력 배치 혐의로 비난 그리고 반역적인 야망을 품고 있습니다.
We supported Biantang this time,
이번에는 비안탕을 응원했습니다
severely defeated Great Yan,
Great Yan을 심하게 패배시켰습니다
and resolved the crisis between Great Yong and Great Yan.
그리고 위기를 해결했다 Great Yong과 Great Yan 사이.
My father is wise.
나의 아버지는 현명하시다.
He will surely understand.
그 사람도 분명 이해해 줄 거예요.
Your Highness.
전하.
In my opinion,
내 생각에는
just to be on the safe side,
그냥 안전을 위해서
you should personally write a memorial to explain the reasons.
넌 개인적으로 추모문을 써야 해 이유를 설명하기 위해.
I will send an urgent courier
긴급택배를 보내드릴게요
to deliver it back to Zhenhuangcheng,
Zhenhuangcheng에게 다시 전달하려면
just in case.
혹시라도.
No need.
필요하지 않습니다.
Report truthfully.
사실대로 신고하세요.
If Father really wants to blame me,
아버지가 정말로 나를 비난하고 싶으시다면,
what's the use of me petitioning personally?
무슨 소용이야? 내가 개인적으로 청원하는 거야?
His Majesty is so partial to the Thirteenth Prince.
폐하께서는 너무 부분적입니다. 열세 번째 왕자에게.
It is truly unfair to you.
그것은 당신에게 정말 불공평합니다.
Is that something you should say?
그게 꼭 말해야 할 일인가요?
I just feel wronged for you.
난 그냥 당신 때문에 억울한 느낌이 듭니다.
For years, you have been guarding the border,
수년 동안, 당신은 국경을 지키고 있었습니다.
risking your life for Great Yong.
그레이트 용을 위해 목숨을 걸고.
In the end, you were suppressed
결국 당신은 진압당했어요
by a wet-behind-the-ears brat.
귀 뒤가 젖은 녀석에 의해.
Enough!
충분한!
Forgive me.
용서해주세요.
Guards, prepare my horse.
경비병들이여, 내 말을 준비하라.
A bowl of noodles, please.
국수 한 그릇 주세요.
Would you like to try our signature
우리의 서명을 시험해 보시겠습니까
roast lamb leg?
구운 양 다리?
No, thanks.
아니요, 고마워요.
Sir, sir.
선생님, 선생님.
You must have come from afar, right?
분명 멀리서 오셨겠죠?
Come, have a seat.
자, 앉으세요.
Please come inside, sir.
안으로 들어오세요, 선생님.
Please, sit.
앉으세요.
Sir, what would you like to eat?
선생님, 무엇을 드시겠어요?
A bowl of noodles, a side dish,
국수 한 그릇, 반찬,
and a pot of wine.
그리고 와인 한 병.
Would you like to try our signature
우리의 서명을 시험해 보시겠습니까
roast lamb leg?
구운 양 다리?
Okay.
좋아요.
Coming right up.
바로 올라옵니다.
Sir, your wine.
선생님, 와인입니다.
The noodles will be ready in a moment.
잠시 후면이 준비됩니다.
Sir, your noodles.
선생님, 국수입니다.
Delicious roast lamb leg.
맛있는 구운 양고기 다리.
Everything is first come, first served.
모든 것은 선착순입니다.
Why did you serve him first?
왜 먼저 그를 섬겼습니까?
Enjoy your meal.
식사를 즐기십시오.
Why are you so unreasonable?
왜 그렇게 불합리한가요?
Forget it.
잊어버리세요.
Give it to her.
그녀에게 주세요.
Two more pots of wine.
와인 두 병 더.
Hurry.
서두르다.
Warm up two pots of wine for the gentleman.
와인 두 병을 따뜻하게 데우세요 신사를 위해.
Sir, you obviously look like
선생님, 당신은 확실히
a generous and blessed man.
관대하고 축복받은 사람.
Not like some poor beggars.
가난한 거지들과는 다릅니다.
They may have little money, but they're very demanding.
돈이 거의 없을 수도 있지만, 하지만 그들은 매우 까다롭습니다.
Enjoy your meal.
식사를 즐기십시오.
Don't mind him, miss.
그 사람은 신경쓰지 마세요, 아가씨.
These noodles are on me.
이 국수는 나에게 있습니다.
I am just passing through.
저는 그냥 지나가고 있는 중이에요.
May I ask if you are from this town?
당신이 이 마을 출신인지 물어봐도 될까요?
Miss,
아가씨,
have you seen my purse?
내 지갑 봤어?
Two suspicious-looking beggars
의심스러워 보이는 두 명의 거지
just passed by you.
방금 당신 곁을 지나갔습니다.
It was probably stolen.
아마도 도난당한 것 같습니다.
Since you saw it,
그걸 본 이후로
why did you let them go?
왜 그들을 놓아줬나요?
In a little shop in the middle of nowhere like this,
작은 가게에서 이런 외딴 곳에
dressing so flashily makes you
너무 화려하게 옷을 입으면 당신은
an easy target.
쉬운 목표.
Who else would they steal from?
또 누구에게서 훔치겠습니까?
I'll pay for my own noodles.
국수값은 내가 직접 지불하겠습니다.
You don't need to do it.
당신은 그것을 할 필요가 없습니다.
Miss!
놓치다!
My horse?
내 말?
Why are you following me?
왜 나를 따라오나요?
I have a favor to ask.
부탁드릴 게 있어요.
The thieves in the tavern
선술집의 도둑들
not only stole my purse,
내 지갑을 훔쳤을 뿐만 아니라
but also my horse.
하지만 내 말도 마찬가지야.
My companions are waiting for me 30 li away.
동료들이 나를 기다리고 있다 30리 떨어져 있어요.
I can't afford to waste time.
시간을 낭비할 여유가 없어요.
So I'd like to ask you to lend me a horse.
그래서 말을 빌려달라고 부탁하고 싶습니다.
Why does everyone want to borrow a horse from me?
다들 왜 그래? 나한테 말 빌릴래?
Once I return home,
집에 돌아오면
I will repay you 10 times the price.
가격의 10배로 갚아드리겠습니다.
Not enough?
충분하지 않습니까?
You can take advantage of the situation.
상황을 활용할 수 있습니다.
Take advantage?
활용하시겠습니까?
You're a step too late.
당신은 너무 늦었어요.
My horse has already been borrowed.
내 말은 이미 빌렸어요.
Now all I have left is this donkey used for milling.
이제 나에게 남은 건 이 당나귀는 제분에 사용됩니다.
I really can't help you.
나는 정말로 당신을 도울 수 없습니다.
You'd better find another way.
다른 방법을 찾는 게 좋을 것 같아요.
Miss...
아가씨...
[I will repay your kindness for lending me the donkey.]
[당신의 은혜에 보답하겠습니다. 나에게 당나귀를 빌려줘서.]
Repay?
갚다?
I think it'd be great for General Chu
추 장군에게 좋을 것 같아요
to stay in Biantang.
비안탕에 머물다.
She will definitely meet a gentleman from Biantang in the future
그녀는 반드시 신사를 만날 것이다 미래에는 비안탕에서
who is more handsome, more skilled
누가 더 잘생겼고, 더 능숙한가
and loves her more than you do.
그리고 당신보다 그녀를 더 사랑해요.
He will fall for her, move her,
그는 그녀에게 반할 것이고, 그녀를 감동시킬 것이다
and then marry her.
그리고 그녀와 결혼하세요.
From then on, she can live
그때부터 그녀는 살 수 있다
a happy and fulfilling life in Biantang.
비안탕에서 행복하고 충만한 삶을 누리세요.
Then you can go back to Great Yong
그럼 그레이트 용에게 돌아가면 돼
and keep being Young Master Zhuge.
계속해서 Young Master Zhuge로 지내세요.
Wait.
기다리다.
There is another possibility.
또 다른 가능성이 있습니다.
You can stay in Biantang until the poison flares up.
비안탕에 묵으시면 됩니다 독이 터질 때까지.
Once you're dead,
네가 죽으면,
you'll become someone irreplaceable in her heart,
넌 대체불가한 사람이 될 거야 마음속으로
and she'll remember you for the rest of her life.
그러면 그녀는 당신을 기억할 거예요 그녀의 남은 생애 동안.
You are a doctor.
당신은 의사입니다.
Doctors rely on observation, auscultation, inquiry, and palpation,
의사는 관찰, 청진, 문의 및 촉진,
not on nagging.
잔소리 안 하고.
Let me tell you.
내가 당신에게 말해 보자.
You refuse to tell General Chu about your condition
당신은 추 장군에게 말하기를 거부했습니다. 당신의 상태에 대해
and have delayed here for so long.
그리고 여기서 너무 오랫동안 지체했어요.
When the poison enters your heart,
독이 당신의 마음에 들어가면,
even if I get the antidote from Ximeng,
Ximeng에게서 해독제를 얻어도
I won't be able to save you.
나는 당신을 구할 수 없습니다.
Then you can just wait for me
그럼 그냥 기다리시면 됩니다
to use your body for research.
연구를 위해 몸을 사용합니다.
Help!
돕다!
What happened?
무슨 일이에요?
Young Master Zhuge,
젊은 스승 Zhuge,
who is this person?
이 사람은 누구입니까?
He said he was looking for you
그 사람이 당신을 찾고 있다고 하더군요
and then collapsed here.
그러다가 여기서 무너졌어요.
He is badly injured.
그는 심하게 다쳤습니다.
It's probably from torture.
아마도 고문 때문일 겁니다.
I have given him medicine,
나는 그에게 약을 주었어요
but I don't know when he will wake up.
하지만 그 사람이 언제 깨어날지 모르겠어요.
This piece of leather was found in his clothes.
이 가죽 조각 그의 옷에서 발견되었습니다.
This belongs to the Queen of Lingyue.
이것은 Lingyue 여왕의 것입니다.
She is in danger in Ximeng.
그녀는 Ximeng에서 위험에 처해 있습니다.
You mean...
그러니까...
The Ximeng delegation had an accident in Biantang,
시멍 대표단 비안탕에서 사고가 났어요
and only the Queen of Lingyue and Baze returned.
그리고 링웨의 여왕만이 그리고 Baze가 돌아 왔습니다.
King Ximeng might not easily let them go.
Ximeng 왕은 쉽게 그들을 놓아주지 않을 수도 있습니다.
Young Master,
젊은 스승님,
Miss Chu is back.
미스 츄가 돌아왔습니다.
Got it.
알았어요.
Young Master,
젊은 스승님,
Miss Chu...
미스 추...
you must not let Miss Chu stay here.
미스 추를 여기에 머물게 해서는 안 됩니다.
Even if not for yourself,
자신을 위한 것이 아니더라도
think of her.
그녀를 생각해보세요.
How many times have you faced death together
몇 번이나 함께 죽음을 맞이한 적이 있나요
to get to this point?
이 지점까지 가려면?
Young Master, say something.
영스승님, 말씀 좀 해주세요.
Ask Miss Chu to go with you.
미스 추에게 같이 가자고 하세요.
I will stay in Tangjing for a few more days.
나는 탕징에 머물 것이다 며칠 더.
I killed the Prince of Luo
내가 루오 왕자를 죽였어
for my own selfish reasons.
나 자신의 이기적인 이유로.
I wanted to avenge Li Ce.
나는 리세의 복수를 하고 싶었다.
But I can't let the current Biantang
하지만 현재의 비안탕을 놔둘 수는 없어요
fall into a new crisis.
새로운 위기에 빠진다.
The royal clan is now circling like vultures.
왕실 일족 지금은 독수리처럼 맴돌고 있습니다.
The moment I leave,
내가 떠나는 순간,
those princes
그 왕자들
will form cliques.
파벌을 형성하게 됩니다.
Li Ce helped me.
Li Ce가 나를 도왔습니다.
I couldn't save him.
나는 그를 구할 수 없었다.
But I want to protect Biantang for him.
하지만 나는 그를 위해 비안탕을 지켜주고 싶다.
Only by becoming the Empress
황후가 됨으로써만
can I take charge of the overall situation.
내가 맡을 수 있을까? 전반적인 상황의.
I understand.
이해합니다.
I understand everything you said.
나는 당신이 말한 모든 것을 이해합니다.
But you haven't recovered yet,
하지만 아직 회복되지 않았네요,
and you've been exhausted for days.
그리고 당신은 며칠 동안 지쳤어요.
Let me send you back first.
먼저 보내드리겠습니다.
No need.
필요하지 않습니다.
You should go to bed early too.
너도 일찍 자야 해.
Xing,
싱,
no matter what you want to do,
무엇을 하고 싶든 상관없어요
I will always wait for you.
나는 항상 당신을 기다릴 것입니다.
No matter whether it's the Biantang royal clan surrounding us
그러든말든 상관없어 우리를 둘러싸고 있는 변당왕족
or the treacherous tides of change,
아니면 위험한 변화의 파도,
nothing can tear us apart anymore.
더 이상 그 무엇도 우리를 갈라놓을 수 없습니다.
One day,
어느 날,
we will surely fight side by side
우리는 반드시 나란히 싸울 것이다
and walk hand in hand.
그리고 손을 잡고 걸어보세요.
Oh, no.
안 돼.
It's all over now.
이제 다 끝났습니다.
[Three days later]
[3일 후]
The wedding of the Empress Dowager and the late emperor...
황태후의 결혼식 그리고 죽은 황제...
It's the first time I've heard of something like this.
처음이에요 나는 이런 말을 들은 적이 있다.
Yes.
예.
We've never seen the style of this wedding carriage.
우리는 그런 스타일을 본 적이 없어 이 결혼식 마차의.
The star and moon lanterns on it
그 위에 별과 달 등불이 달려있어
don't seem to be commonly used in Biantang.
일반적으로 사용되지 않는 것 같습니다 비앙탕에서.
Xing,
싱,
something happened to the Ximeng delegation.
무슨 일이 일어났어 Ximeng 대표단에게.
I must depart for Ximeng immediately.
나는 즉시 시멍(Ximeng)으로 출발해야 ​​합니다.
You are staying in Biantang to manage the crisis,
당신은 비안탕에 머물고 있습니다 위기를 관리하기 위해
and this will inevitably draw the hostility of various forces.
그리고 이것은 필연적으로 다양한 세력의 적대감을 그려보세요.
I'm leaving the 500 guards
500명의 경비병을 떠날 거야
Li Ce promised me to you.
Li Ce가 당신에게 약속했습니다.
They can help me protect you.
내가 당신을 보호하는 데 도움이 될 수 있어요.
This blood pigeon is raised by the Queen of Lingyue.
이 피비둘기를 키웠어요 링웨 여왕에 의해.
It recognizes its owner.
주인을 알아봅니다.
If you need anything in the future,
앞으로 필요한 것이 있으면
you can bring it to Ximeng and find me.
Ximeng으로 가져가면 나를 찾을 수 있습니다.
The antidote Xiao Ran prepared for me
샤오란이 나를 위해 준비한 해독제
can delay the onset of the Blood on Snow in my body.
발병을 늦출 수 있다 내 몸에 쌓인 눈의 피.
You don't need to worry about me.
나에 대해 걱정할 필요가 없습니다.
Lady Chu,
추 부인,
these are the Moon-star Lanterns Young Master Zhuge
이게 바로 달별 랜턴이에요 젊은 스승 제갈
specially prepared for you.
당신을 위해 특별히 준비했습니다.
Moon-star Lantern?
달별 랜턴?
Exactly.
정확히.
So beautiful.
너무 아름다워요.
Yeah.
응.
Young Master,
젊은 스승님,
after crossing this mountain,
이 산을 넘은 후
we will be out of Biantang's territory.
우리는 Biantang의 영역을 벗어나게 될 것입니다.
It's the direction of Tangjing.
탕징 방향입니다.
It's fireworks for a celebration in the palace.
불꽃놀이야 궁전에서 축하를 위해.
From this day on,
오늘부터
Biantang abolishes slave status
Biantang은 노예 신분을 폐지합니다
and prohibits the slave trade.
그리고 노예무역을 금지합니다.
Who sent you here?
누가 당신을 여기로 보냈나요?
Have you fallen in love with him?
그와 사랑에 빠졌나요?
What exactly are you trying to say?
정확히 무엇을 말하려는 건가요?
I want to know King Ximeng's weakness.
시멍왕의 약점을 알고 싶습니다.
No!
아니요!
Whether your people can live
당신의 사람들이 살 수 있을지
depends entirely
전적으로 의존한다
on you.
당신에.
Zhuge Yue is dying.
Zhuge Yue가 죽어가고 있습니다.
Zhuge Yue!
제갈유에!